[
{
  "question": "Can you explain efficiency and what is necessary for a process to achieve maximum efficiency in a heat engine?",
  "answer": "Efficiency is defined as the fraction of heat input that is turned into actual work, also equal to 1 - (heat output)/(heat input). There must be a limit to efficiency as a consequence of the Kelvin-Planck Statement, which states that “It is impossible to construct a cyclic device whose sole effect is to produce positive work whilst receiving heat from a single reservoir.” In other words, you cannot achieve 100% efficiency, where all heat from a single source is converted to work. Maximum efficiency is achieved when the process is reversible, that is, when the system and surroundings can be returned to their initial states. A reversible process will not greatly depart from equilibrium, meaning that it is a quasi-equilibrium process that generally occurs slowly. In the case of a reversible process, the efficiency is equal to 1 - (final temperature)/(initial temperature). This relationship can be derived using the Clausius Inequality."
},
{
  "question": "Why are constant volume lines always steeper than constant pressure lines on T-s diagrams?",
  "answer": "To answer this question, we must first define specific heat capacity, which is the heat required to raise the temperature of one kilogram of a substance by one degree Kelvin. We define them at both constant pressure (c_p) and at constant volume (c_v). For a given gas, the value of c_p is always greater than the value of c_v, because increasing volume requires work, which takes up some of the energy used to raise the temperature in a constant pressure process; consequently, more energy is required for a temperature increase when volume changes and pressure is constant. For a perfect gas at constant pressure, Tds = c_pdT, so the gradient of the T-s curve equals T/c_p. Similarly, for a perfect gas at constant volume, Tds=c_vdT, and the gradient is T/c_v. Since c_p is always greater than c_v, T/c_v will always be greater than T/c_p, resulting in a steeper slope."
},
{
  "question": "How can one tell if a process is isentropic, and how does evaluating such a process differ from evaluating a process with a change in entropy?",
  "answer": "An isentropic process, as the name implies, is characterized by its zero change in entropy (s_2=s_1). An isentropic process is adiabatic, meaning that the system and surroundings exchange no heat (Q=0); this is often achieved by performing the process almost instantaneously or using insulating walls. An isentropic process must also be reversible, meaning that the system and surroundings can be returned to their initial states. An example of a statement of an isentropic process is “A mass of air is compressed rapidly within a cylinder by a piston. You may assume the compression is reversible.” An advantage of evaluating isentropic processes is that one can apply the isentropic changes, which relate temperature, pressure, density, volume, and specific volume (assuming the substance is an ideal gas)."
},
{
  "question": "Can you explain Fanno Flow and why crossing from one branch to another on the T-s diagram is not possible?",
  "answer": "Fanno Flow is the model of flow through a very long pipe with friction. As length increases, this friction decreases the effective area, increasing velocity in subsonic flows and decreasing velocity in supersonic flows. In both cases, this leads to a choked flow at a certain length L. This choke occurs at maximum entropy, and it represents a discontinuity on the T-s diagram. One cannot “cross over” from the supersonic to subsonic branch, or vice versa, because moving along the other curve would result in a decrease in entropy, which is not possible for the moving flow subject to friction."
},
{
  "question": "Can you explain the difference between Couette Flow and Poiseuille Flow and what happens when they are combined?",
  "answer": "Both models consider steady, viscous flow with straight streamlines parallel to the plates. between two parallel plates. The main assumptions are that the flow is incompressible and the plates are very wide and very long. In Couette Flow, one of the plates moves parallel to the other plate with some velocity (v), and the pressure gradient is zero. This yields a linear fluid velocity profile with boundary conditions stating that at the stationary plate, the velocity of the fluid equals zero, and at the moving plate the fluid velocity is equal to the plate velocity. In contrast, Poiseuille Flow occurs between two stationary plates and is induced by a constant pressure gradient. The resulting fluid velocity profile is parabolic equal to zero at the plates and reaching a maximum at half the distance between the plates. Combining the two models, that is, having both a moving plate and a nonzero pressure gradient, yields a parabolic fluid velocity profile with different boundary conditions. Note that if the pressure gradient opposes the moving plate’s velocity, the fluid velocity near the stationary plate may reverse.",
	"references": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
},
{
  "question": "What is the point of measuring both static and stagnation pressure with a pitot tube in incompressible flow? What makes static pressure different from stagnation pressure?",
  "answer": "A pitot tube measures static pressure from an opening that is oriented perpendicular to the direction of the flow. This measurement does not take the fluid’s velocity into account, so it is the “actual” pressure that you would experience if you were moving at the same velocity as the flow. If a question asks you about pressure, you may assume that it is referring to static pressure. The stagnation pressure of the flow is measured by an opening that faces the flow, creating a stagnation point where the velocity is zero. It represents the pressure of the fluid if it were brought to rest with no mechanical losses. Knowing both of these values allows you to calculate the flow’s velocity with Bernoulli’s equation: p_1 + rho*(v_1)^2 = p_2 + rho*(v_2)^2, where p_1 is the static pressure, rho is the density, v_1 is the flow velocity, p_2 is the stagnation pressure, and v_2 is the velocity at the stagnation point, which is zero. Please note that we neglected the effects of gravity, and since the flow is incompressible, the density is equal at both points.",
	"references": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
},
{
  "question": "On the Oblique Shock Tables, why are there two rows for a given turning angle theta, and which row should be used?",
  "answer": "The two rows represent the values for weak and strong shocks at a given turning angle, with weak being the row appearing first from top to bottom and the strong last for a given theta. A weak shock is more likely to happen, and it is characterized by a smaller wave angle beta and a supersonic Mach number behind it. Conversely, strong shocks are associated with larger wave angles and have subsonic flow behind them. These are far less common, so when solving a problem involving oblique shocks, it is usually safe to assume the shock was weak and use the higher row corresponding to the given theta. Additionally, if you have a problem with multiple shocks, the earlier shocks must be weak, because a strong shock makes the proceeding flow subsonic and thus negates the possibility of subsequent shocks.",
	"references": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
},
{
  "question": "Why do expansion fans alter the flow properties (pressure, Mach number, etc.) opposite to normal and oblique shocks?",
  "answer": "A large difference between expansion fans and oblique shocks has to do with entropy. An expansion fan is modeled as a continuous expansion region with infinitesimal Mach waves. Because these waves are continuous, the change in entropy across an expansion fan is isentropic, whereas the discontinuity present in an oblique shock causes an increase in entropy. In expansion fans, Mach number increases, density and static pressure decrease, and stagnation pressure remains constant. However, in oblique shocks, the wave “turns into itself,” resulting in a drop in Mach number and stagnation pressure, and an increase in density, static pressure, and entropy.",
	"references": [
    "https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/centered-expansion-fan/#:~:text=Across%20a%20shock%20wave%2C%20the,Expansion%20fans%20are%20isentropic.",
    "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill." 
    ]
},
{
  "question": "Can you elaborate on the two-property rule in thermodynamics and when it is applied?",
  "answer": "The two-property rule states that two independent, intensive properties must be specified to define the state of a substance. An intensive property is one that is not dependent on the system size, like specific volume. A property is independent if it can be held constant while the other changes; for example, specific volume and temperature are always independent and can therefore be used to define a system. This rule is applied to simple compressible systems of pure substances: substances that have uniform and unchanging chemical composition. This model neglects the effects of gravity, motion, surface tension, and electricity.",
	"references": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
},
{
  "question": "A gas of density 1.7 kg/m^3 flows through a pipe with a volume flow rate of 0.12 m^3/s. The pipe has an inlet section diameter of d_1 of 21 cm and an outlet section diameter d_2 of 9 cm. Assuming an ideal incompressible fluid flow, calculate the flow velocities at the pipe's inlet and outlet, i.e., V_1 and V_2, respectively.",
  "answer": {
      "code": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nQ = 0.12 # Volumetric flow rate ((m^3)/s)\nd_in = 0.21 # Inlet diameter (m)\nd_out = 0.09 # Outlet diameter (m)\npi = 3.14\n# Calculate inlet and outlet areas\nA_in = (1/4) * pi * (d_in **2)\nA_out = (1/4) * pi * (d_out ** 2)\n \n# Calculate inlet and outlet velocities\nv_in = Q / A_in # Inlet velocity\nprint("Inlet velocity:", v_in, "m/s")\nv_out = Q / A_out # Outlet velocity\nprint("Outlet velocity:", v_out, "m/s")\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the initial and final velocities of a flow going through a pipe with variable area. We assume the flow is inviscid and incompressible (density is constant), and thus utilize the equation Q = Av, where Q is the volumetric flow rate, A is the cross-sectional area, and v is the velocity. Additionally, continuity applies, so Q_in = Q_out.",
      "references": "https://eaglepubs.erau.edu/introductiontoaerospaceflightvehicles/chapter/worked-examples-fluid-flows/",
  }
},
{
  "question": "A garden hose attached with a nozzle is used to fill a 10-gal bucket. The inner diameter of the hose is 2 cm, and it reduces to 0.8 cm at the nozzle exit. If it takes 50 s to fill the bucket with water, determine (a) the volume and mass flow rates of water through the hose, and (b) the average velocity of water at the nozzle exit",
  "answer": {
      "code": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nvGallon = 10 # Volume (gallons)\nt = 50 # Time to fill (s)\nrho = 1000 # Density of water (kg/m^2)\npi = 3.14 # Constant\nd = .008 # Diameter of hose nozzle (m)\nr = d / 2 # Radius of hose nozzle (m)\narea = pi*(r**2) # Area of hose nozzle (m^2)\n\n# Convert gallons to m^3\nvMeter = vGallon / 264.2\n\n# Volumetric flow rate\nQ = vMeter / t\n\n# Mass flow rate\nmDot = Q * rho\nprint("Volumetric flow rate:", Q, "m^3/s")\nprint("Mass flow rate:", mDot, "kg/s")\n\n# Average velocity\navgVelocity = Q / area\nprint("Average velocity:", avgVelocity, "m/s")\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the volumetric flow rate using the formula Q = V / t, where Q is the volumetric flow rate and V is the volume filled in time t. The mass flow rate is calculated with the formula Mdot = Q * rho, where rho is the density of water in kg / m^2. Assuming that water is incompressible and the flow through the hose is steady, we calculated Vavg = Q / A, where A is the cross-sectional area of the hose nozzle. Please note that units were converted to SI units where applicable (ie cm to m)",
      "references": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
  }
},
{
  "question": "A piston-cylinder device initially contains air at 150 kPa and 27°C. At this state, the piston is resting on a pair of stops and the enclosed volume is 400 L. The mass of the piston is such that a 350-kPa pressure is required to move it. The air is now heated until its volume has doubled. Determine (a) the final temperature and (b) the work done by the air.",
  "answer": {
      "code": "\nimport numpy as np\n\np1 = 150000 # Initial pressure (Pa)\np2 = 350000 # Final pressure (Pa)\nt1_celcius = 27 # Initial temperature (Celcius)\nt1 = t1_celcius + 273.15 # Convert initial temperature to Kelvin\nv1_liter = 400 # Initial volume (L)\nv1 = v1_liter/1000 # Convert volume to m^3\nv2 = 2 * v1 # Final volume (m^3)\n\n# Use ideal gas law to calculate final temperature\nt2 = (t1 * p2 * v2) / (p1 * v1)\nprint("Final temperature:", t2, "K")\n\n# Calculate work done using P*delta(V)\nw = p2 * (v2-v1)\nprint("Work done:", w, "J")\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the change in temperature of work done by air that is heated to move a piston. Since we are given the initial and final pressure and volume, we can make use of the ideal gas relations to find the final temperature: (P1 * V1) / T1 = (P2 * V2) / T2, where P1 and P2 are the initial and final pressures, V1 and V2 are the initial and final volumes, and T1 and T2 are the initial and final temperatures. Please note that the temperature is given in degrees Celcius and must be converted to Kelvin. The work was then found by using the definition of P-V work: W = P2 * (V2 - V1), where W represents the work done by the gas in Joules. Note that we assume air acts as an ideal gas, changes in potential and kinetic energy are negligible, and that no shaft work is present.",
      "references": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
  }
},
{
  "question": "Air at 10°C and 80 kPa enters the diffuser of a jet engine steadily with a velocity of 200 m/s. The inlet area of the diffuser is 0.4 m^2. The air leaves the diffuser with a velocity that is very small compared with the inlet velocity. Determine (a) the mass flow rate of the air and (b) the change in specific enthalpy of the air leaving the diffuser.",
  "answer": {
      "code": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1_celcius = 10 # Initial temperature (Celcius)\nT1 = T1_celcius + 273.15 # Convert T1 to Kelvin\np1 = 80000 # Initial pressure (Pa)\nA_in = 0.4 # Inlet area (m^2)\nv1 = 200 # Initial velocity (m/s)\nv2 = 0 # Final velocity << v1 (m/s)\nR = 287 # Gas constant for air (J/(kg*K))\ncp = 1005 # Specific heat of air at constant pressure (J/(kg*K))\n\n# Calculate specific volume using ideal gas law\nspecific_volume = (R * T1) / p1 # Specific volume (m^3/kg)\nrho = 1 / specific_volume\n\n# Calculate mass flow rate\nmDot = rho * v1 * A_in\nprint("Mass flow rate:", mDot, "kg/s")\n\n# Calculate change in specific enthalpy\ndelta_h = - (((v2**2)-(v1**2))/2) # Steady Flow Energy Equation\nprint("Change in specific enthalpy:", delta_h, "J/kg")\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the mass flow rate and change in specific enthalpy of subsonic flow through a nozzle. To begin, we assume that this is a steady-flow process, so the mass flow rate in equals the mass flow rate out. We also assume a negligible change in potential energy, that the kinetic energy at the exit is zero due to the low velocity, and that air behaves as an ideal gas. The mass flow rate was found by first finding the specific volume using ideal gas relations (nu = (R * T) / P) and using it to find the density (rho = 1 / nu), where nu is the specific volume, R is the gas constant for air, T is the temperature, P is the pressure, and rho is the density; then, mass flow rate was found using rho * v1 * A_in, where v1 is the initial velocity and A_in is the inlet area. The change in specific enthalpy was found by algebraic manipulation of the Steady Flow Energy Equation: h1 + ((v1 ** 2) / 2) = h2 + ((v2 ** 2) / 2), where h1 and h2 are the initial and final enthalpies, and v1 and v2 are the initial and final velocities, respectively. Please note again that we assumed v2 = 0.",
      "references": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
  }
},
{
  "question": "A rigid tank contains a hot fluid that is cooled while being stirred by a paddle wheel. Initially, the internal energy of the fluid is 800 kJ. During the cooling process, the fluid loses 500 kJ of heat, and the paddle wheel does 100 kJ of work on the fluid. Determine the final internal energy of the fluid. Neglect the energy stored in the paddle wheel.",
  "answer": {
      "code": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nU1 = 800000 # Initial internal energy (J)\nQ = -500000 # Heat lost to surroundings from system (J)\nW = -100000 # Work done on system by paddle (J)\n\n# Calculate change in internal energy\ndelta_U = Q - W\nU2 = delta_U + U1\nprint("Final internal energy:", U2, "J")\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the final internal energy of a system with heat loss and work input using the First Law equation Q - W = U2 - U1, where Q and W are the heat input and work output respectively, and U2 and U1 are the final and initial internal energies. Please note that for this problem, Q is negative because heat is lost to the system, and W is negative because work is done on the system. We assume the kinetic and potential energy changes are zero and that no boundary work is being done by the system since the container is rigid.",
	    "references": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
  }
},
{
  "question": "Air enters a diffuser shown in with a velocity of 200 m/s. Determine (a) the speed of sound and (b) the Mach number at the diffuser inlet when the air temperature is 30°C.",
  "answer": {
      "code": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv = 200 # Velocity (m/s)\nT_celcius = 30 # Temperature (Celcius)\nT = T_celcius + 273.15 # Convert temperature (K)\ngamma = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio of air\nR = 287 # Gas constant for air (J/kgK)\n\n# Calculate speed of sound (m/s)\na = (gamma * R * T) ** (1/2)\nprint("Speed of sound:", a, "m/s")\n\n# Calculate Mach number\nM = v/a\nprint("Mach number:", M)\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the speed of sound in air for the given conditions using the equation a = (gamma * R * T) ** (1/2), where a is the speed of sound, gamma is the specific heat ratio, R is the gas constant, and T is the temperature. The Mach number is then calculated using M = v/a, where v is the velocity and a is the speed of sound for the given conditions. To perform these calculations, we assume that air behaves as an ideal gas.",
	    "references": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
  }
},
{
  "question": "Air enters a converging-diverging nozzle at 1.0 MPa and 800 K with a negligible velocity. The flow is steady, one-dimensional, and isentropic with gamma = 1.4. For an exit Mach number of Ma = 2 and a throat area of 20 cm^2, determine the temperature and pressure at the throat.",
  "answer": {
      "code": "\nimport numpy as np\n\np0 = 1000000 # Inlet stagnation pressure (Pa)\nT0 = 800 # Inlet stagnation temperature (K)\npStar_p0 = 0.5283 # Static to stagnation pressure ratio at Mach 1 (found on table)\nTstar_T0 = 0.8333 # Temperature ratio at Mach 1 (found on table)\n\n# Use values from table to find pressure and temperature at throat\npStar = pStar_p0 * p0\nprint("Static pressure at throat", pStar, "Pa")\nTstar = Tstar_T0 * T0\nprint("Temperature at throat", Tstar, "K")\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the pressure and temperature conditions at the throat of a converging-diverging nozzle. Please note that some values used in the calculation must be found on Gas Flow Tables. The throat temperature was found by the equation T = (T / T0) * T0, where (T / T0) is the temperature ratio at Mach 1 found on the table and T0 is the given stagnation temperature. The static pressure in the throat was similarly found by p = (p / p0) * p0, where (p / p0) is the pressure ratio at Mach 1 and p0 is the given stagnation pressure. To calculate this, we assume that the flow is steady, one-dimensional, and isentropic, and that air is an ideal gas.",
	    "references": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill.",
  }
}
]